Guide to the James F. Ahern Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
James F. Ahern papers
1954-2017
MS 2086
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.34
(42 boxes)
The collection consists of the personal papers of James F. Ahern, documenting his position as chief of police for New Haven, Connecticut.
Biographical / Historical
James F. Ahern was born in New Haven, Connecticut, in 1932. Ahern first joined the New Haven Police Department as a patrolman in 1954, and in 1968 was appointed police chief. Ahern presided as police chief in 1970 during the May Day student protests at Yale University and the New Haven Black Panthers trial. Ahern was credited for his efforts to diffuse the tense situation surrounding the protests and ensure they did not become violent. After leaving the New Haven Police Department in 1970, Ahern became a critic of violent police tactics, authoring a book, Police in Trouble: Our Frightening Crisis in Law Enforcement. In 1970 Ahern served on the President's Commission on Campus Unrest (also known as the Scranton Commission), which investigated violent clashes between college students and police at Kent State University and Jackson State University. He also served as director of the Insurance Crime Prevention Institute in Westport, Connecticut until his retirement in 1982. Ahern died in 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The papers are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jennifer G. Ahern, 2018.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the personal papers of James F. Ahern, documenting his position as chief of police for New Haven, Connecticut. Included are materials related to student and police activities during May Day 1970 at Yale University, wiretapping by the New Haven police, and Ahern's role as a member of the President's Commission on Campus Unrest in 1970. Also included are photographs of Ahern, posters, magazine articles authored by and concerning Ahern, audio and visual recordings of Ahern's media appearances, scrapbooks with speeches and news clippings, correspondence by Ahern and family, and Rolodex cards with names and contact information for Ahern's colleagues in police administration.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven groupings: New Haven Police Department, President's Commission on Campus Unrest, Speeches and writings, Scrapbooks and printed media, Correspondence, Photographs, and Audiovisual material.
Police patrol -- Surveillance operations; Student protesters; Campus police
- New Haven Police Department
  - May Day reports, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Wiretapping case, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rolodex cards, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Rolodex cards, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Rolodex cards, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Address cards, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Business cards, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Post-retirement
    - Certificate appointing James F. Ahern honorary lieutenant colonel in Rhode Island State Police, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Certificates, 1978-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - A survey of the political climate in New Haven, Connecticut, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Transcript of telephone conversation between James F. Ahern and Fred Cronan, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- President's Commission on Campus Unrest
  - Certificate appointing James Ahern to the President's Commission on Campus Unrest, signed by United States Secretary of State William Rogers and President Richard Nixon, 1970 (Box 14)
  - Commission final report draft, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - The Report of the President's Commission on Campus Unrest, bound copy, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Speeches and writings
  Scope and Contents
  Includes speeches and written material by James F. Ahern documenting his views on policing and police reform.
  - Book material for Police in Trouble, circa 1972 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Book outline for Police in Trouble, circa 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Book review, Cops and Rebels: A Study of Provocation, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Democratic Control and Professional Restraint", reprinted from The Great Ideas Today, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Interview for director of the FBI, circa 1970s (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Magazine articles, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Meet the Press interview transcript, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
    Includes a speech by Ahern about the 1970 Kent State shootings.
- Scrapbooks and printed media
  Scrapbooks contain newspaper clippings, articles, and photographs related to James Ahern and the New Haven Police Department, documenting Ahern's work as a police officer and police reform activist.
  - Ahern, James F., scrapbook, 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 1-12)
  - Ahern, James F., scrapbook, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 1-10)
  - The Grapevine Press, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Insurance Crime Prevention Institute (ICPI) scrapbook, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 2-11)
  - Magazine articles about James Ahern, 1959-1982 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Magazines about police and crime prevention, 1970-2006 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Nadjari, Maurice, articles and press release, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - News clippings about James Ahern and policing, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 4-7)
  - News clippings about James Ahern and policing, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - Newspaper articles on James Ahern and policing, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook with photographs, 1971-1983 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Unbound articles and newspaper clippings, 1967-1972 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Correspondence
  - Ahern, Jennifer, and Steve Curtin, concerning James Ahern research project, 2015-2017 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Barry, Raymond J., 1985 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Brunner, Thomas W., 1985 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - City of New Haven Board of Aldermen, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Conway, William S., 1973 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Hait, William N., 1986 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Harness, Wendall C., 1983 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Hartnett, Donald E., 1986 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Herot, Frederick C., 1983 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - James, Jennifer, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Lee, Richard, 1985-1987 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - McLaughlin, Marilou, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - O'Connor, Thom, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Thier, Samuel O., 1986 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified correspondent, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Photographs
  - "33 Rookie Cops Train Hard to Combat Crime in the Elm City", circa 1954 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Ahern, James F., circa 1960s-1970s (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Ahern, James F., circa 1970s (Box 13, Folder 2-4)
    Includes a portrait and a signed group photograph of President's Commission on Campus Unrest.
  - New Haven and Yale Common Ground poster, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 14)
- Audiovisual material
  Conditions Governing Access
  Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
  - Tape 1, Johnny Carson, circa 1970s-1980s; 1 (Box 15)
  - Tape 2, Face the State (CT), circa 1970s-1980s; 1 (Box 16)
  - Tape 3, ICPI, Johnny Carson, Lee Leonard, Q&A, circa 1970s-1980s; 1 (Box 17)
  - Tape 4, Practice speech, Bill Boggs Midday Live, circa 1970s-1980s; 1 (Box 18)
  - Tape 5, ICPI, Bill Boggs Midday Live, circa 1970s-1980s; 1 (Box 19)
  - Chapter 1, tape 1, and chapter 6, tape 6, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 20)
  - Chapter 1, tape 2 final, and chapter 1, tape 3 final, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 21)
  - Tape 2, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 22)
  - Tape 6, first tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 23)
  - Tape 6, second tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 24)
  - Carefree, Arizona speech, December 10, 11, and 12, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 25)
  - Instructions, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 26)
  - Junior ? speech, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 27)
  - Public Affairs Broadcast Group copy of program number 218, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 28)
  - Statement of Richard ?, 1974; 1 (Box 29)
  - Unidentified tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 30)
  - Unidentified tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 31)
  - Unidentified tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 32)
  - Unidentified tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 33)
  - Westport, 1974; 1 (Box 34)
  - WNHC news, 1971; 1 (Box 35)
  - WNHC news, 1971; 1 (Box 36)
  - Conversation between James F. Ahern and Frank Kelly, 1971; 1 (Box 37)
  - District Attorney tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 38)
  - Telephone conversation 6/16 (A.M.) between Fred Cronan and James Ahern re insurance coverage, City of New Haven, side 2, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 39)
  - Telephone conversation 6/16 (A.M.) between Fred Cronan and James Ahern re insurance coverage, City of New Haven, side 2, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 40)
  - Wagner tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 41)
  - Wagner tape, circa 1970s; 1 (Box 42)